This is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hey, this is Jeremy Jung for Software
Engineering Radio and today I'm talking
to Brian Canantrol. He's the co-founder
and CTO of Oxide Computer Company and he
was previously the CTO of Joint and he
also co-authored the Drace tracing
framework while he was at Sun
Microsystems. Ryan, welcome to Software
Engineering Radio.
Awesome. Thanks for having me. It's
great to be here. you're the CTO of a
company that makes computers, but I
think before we get into that, a lot of
people who build software now that the
actual computer is abstracted away.
They're using AWS or they're using some
kind of cloud service. So, I thought we
could start by talking about data
centers cuz you were previously working
at Joint and I believe you got bought by
Samsung and you've previously talked
about how you had to figure out how do I
run things at Samsung's scale? So,
how how was your experience with that?
What were the challenges there?
Yeah, I mean, so at Joyant and so Joint
was a cloud computing pioneer. We
competed with the likes of AWS and then
later GCP and Azure and we I mean we
were operating at a scale right we had a
bunch of machines a bunch of DCs but
ultimately you know we were a VCbacked
company and you know a small company by
the standards of certainly by Samsung
standards and so when Samsung bought the
company and the reason by the way that
Samsung bought Joy is Samsung's cloud
bill was let's just say it was extremely
March, they were spending an enormous
amount of money every year on the public
cloud and they realized that in order to
secure their fate economically, they had
to be running on their own
infrastructure. Just did not make sense
and there was not really a product that
Samsung could go buy that would give
them that on-prem cloud in that regard.
Like the state of the market was really
no different. And so they went looking
for a company and Badroan. And when we
were on the inside of Samsung, we
learned about Samsung scale. And Samsung
loves to talk about Samsung scale. And I
got to tell you, it is more than just
chest thumping. Like Samsung scale
really is I mean just the the sheer the
number of devices, the number of
customers, just this absolute size. They
really wanted to take us out to levels
of scale certainly that we had not seen.
The reason for buying joint was to be
able to stand up on their own
infrastructure. So they we were going to
go buy we did go buy a bunch of hardware
and I remember just thinking God I hope
Dell is somehow magically better. I hope
the problems that we have seen in the
small, you know, I just remember hoping
and hope it was of course a terrible
strategy and it was a terrible strategy
here too. And the problems that we saw
at the large were and when you scale out
the problems that you see kind of once
or twice you now see all of the time and
they become absolutely debilitating and
we saw a whole series of really
debilitating problems. I mean, it's many
ways like comically debilitating in
terms of showing just how bad the
state-of-the-art app is. And we had I
mean, it should be said we had great
software and great software expertise
and we were controlling our own system
software, but even controlling your own
system software, your own host OS, your
own control plane, which is what we had
at Joyand, ultimately you're pretty
limited. you go. I mean, you've got the
problems that you can obviously solve,
the ones that are in your own software,
but the problems that are beneath you,
the problems that are in the hardware
platform, the problems that are in the
componentry beneath you become the
problems that are in the firmware, those
problems become unresolvable. And they
are deeply deeply frustrating and we
just saw a bunch of them. Again, they
were comical in retrospect. And I'll
give you like a couple of concrete
examples just to give you an idea of
what kind of what you're looking at. One
of the our data centers had really
pathological IO latency. We had a very
database heavy workload and this was
kind of right at the period where you
were still deploying on rotating media
on hard drives. So this is like so an
all flash by did not make economic sense
when we did this in 2016. this probably
be interesting to know like when was the
kind of the last time that actual hard
drives made sense cuz I feel this was
close to it. So we had a a bunch of
pathological IO problems but we had one
data center in which the outliers were
actually quite a bit worse and there was
so much going on in that system. It took
us a long time to figure out like why
and because when you're IO you're seeing
worse IO. I mean naturally you want to
understand like what's the workload
doing? trying to take a first principles
approach. What's the workload doing?
This is a very intensive database
workload to support the object storage
system that we had built called Manta
and the metadata tier was stored in was
we were using Postgress for that and
that was just getting absolutely
slaughtered and ultimately very IO bound
with these kind of pathological IO
latencies and as we trying to like peel
away the layers to figure out what was
going on and I finally had this thing
it's like okay we are seeing at the
device layer, at the disk layer, we are
seeing pathological outliers in this
data center that we're not seeing
anywhere else. And that does not make
any sense. And the thought occurred to
me, I'm like, well, maybe we are do we
have like different a different rev of
firmware on our HGST drives? HGST now
part of WD Western Digital were the
drives we had everywhere. So maybe I had
a firmware bug. had this not be the
first time in my life at all that I
would have a drive firmware issue. And I
went to go pull the firmware rev and I'm
like, Toshiba makes hard drives. So, I
had no idea that Toshiba even made hard
drives, let alone that they were they
were in our data center. I'm like, what
is this? And as it turns out, and this
is, you know, part of the challenge when
you don't have an integrated system,
which not to pick on them, but Dell
doesn't. And what Dell would routinely
put just sub make substitutes and they
make substitutes that they you know it's
kind of like you're going to like I
don't know Instacart or whatever and
they're out of the thing that you want.
So you know you're someone makes a
substitute and like sometimes that's
okay but it's really not okay in a data
center and you really want to develop
and validate an end toend integrated
system and in this case like Toshiba
doesn't I mean Toshiba does make hard
drives but they are a or they did they
basically were not competitive and they
were not competitive in part for the
reasons that we were discovering they
had really serious firmware issues. So
these were drives that would just simply
stop acknowledging any reads for on the
order of 2700 milliseconds. Long time
2.7 seconds. And that was a it was a
drive firmware issue, but it was
highlighted like a much deeper issue
which was the simple lack of control
that we had over our own destiny. And
it's an example among many where Dell is
making a decision that lowers the cost
of what they are providing you
marginally. But it is then giving you a
system that they shouldn't have any
confidence in because it's not one that
they've actually designed. And they
leave it to the customer, the enduser to
make these discoveries. And these things
happen up and down the stack. And for
every for whether it's and not just to
pick on Dell because it's it's true for
HPE, it's true for super micro, it's
true for your switch vendors, it's it's
true for storage vendors where the one
that is left actually integrating these
things and trying to make the whole
thing work is the end user sitting in
their data center. There's not a product
that they can buy that gives them
elastic infrastructure, a cloud in their
own DC. the product that you buy is the
public cloud. Like when you go in the
public cloud, you don't worry about the
stuff because it's AWS's issue or it's
GCP's issue and they are the ones that
get this to ground. And they, and this
was kind of, you know, the eye opening
moment, not a surprise, they are not
Dell customers, they are not HP
customers, they are not super micro
customers. They have designed their own
machines and to varying degrees
depending on which one you're looking
at. But they've taken the clean sheet of
paper and the frustration that we had
kind of at Joy and beginning to wonder
and then Samsung and kind of wondering
what was next is that what they built
was not available for purchase in the
data center. You could only rent it in
the public cloud. And our big belief is
that public cloud computing is a really
important revolution infrastructure.
Doesn't feel like a different deep
thought, but cloud computing is a really
important revolution. It shouldn't only
be available to rent. You should be able
to actually buy it. And there are a
bunch of reasons for doing that. One,
and the one we saw at Samsung is
economics, which I think is still the
dominant reason where it just does not
make sense to rent all of your compute
in perpetuity. But there are other
reasons too. There's security, there's
risk management, there's latency. There
are a bunch of reasons why one might
want to own one's own infrastructure.
But that was very much the the so the
the genesis for oxide was coming out of
this very painful experience and a
painful experience that because I mean a
long answer to your question about like
what was it like to be at Samsung scale
those are the kinds of things that we I
mean in our other data centers we didn't
have Toshiba drives we only had the HDSC
drives but it's only when you get to
this larger scale that you begin to see
some of these pathologies but these
pathologies then are really debilitating
in terms of those who are trying to
develop a service on top of them. So, it
was very educational in that regard and
you're very grateful for the experience
at Samsung in terms of opening our eyes
to the challenge of running at that kind
of scale.
And during that time at Joyant when you
experienced some of these issues, was it
more of a case of you didn't have enough
servers experiencing this? So, if it
would happen, you might say like, well,
this one's not working, so maybe we'll
just replace the hardware. What was the
thought process when you were working at
that smaller scale and and how did these
issues affect you?
Yeah, at the smaller scale you see fewer
of them, right? You just see it's like,
okay, we you know what you might see is
like that's weird. We kind of saw this
in one machine versus seeing it in 100
or a thousand or 10,000. So, you just
see them less frequently. As a result,
they are less debilitating. I think that
it's when you go to that larger scale,
those things that were unusual now
become routine and they become
debilitating. So it it really is in many
regards a function of scale. And then I
think it was also it was a little bit
dispiriting that kind of the substrate
we were building on really had not
improved. And if you buy a computer
server, buy an x86 server, there is a
very low layer of firmware, the bias,
the basic input output system, the UEFI
bias. And this is like an abstraction
layer that is has existed since the 80s
and hasn't really meaningfully improved.
But beyond that, like this lowest layer
of platform enablement software is
really only impeding the operability of
the system. You look at the baseboard
management controller which is the kind
of the computer within the computer.
There is an element in the machine that
needs to handle environmentals that
needs to handle operate the fans and so
on and that traditionally has is the
spaceport management controller and that
architecturally just hasn't improved in
the last two decades. And you know
that's it's a proprietary piece of
silicon generally from a company that no
one's ever heard of called ASPE uh which
has to be is written all in caps. So I
guess it needs to be screamed. ASPE has
a proprietary part. There is a root
password infamously. The root password
is encoded effectively in silicon. And
for anyone who kind of goes deep into
these things, like, oh my god, are you
kidding me? When we first started Oxide,
the Wi-Fi password was a fraction of the
A-speed root password for the BMC. It's
kind of like a little little BMC humor.
But those things, it was just
dispiriting that the state-of-the-art
was still basically personal computers
running in the data center. And that's
part of what was the motivation for
doing something new.
And for the people using these systems,
whether it's the baseboard management
controller or it's the BIOS or UF UEFI
component, what are the actual problems
that people are seeing?
Oh man, you're going to have like some
fraction of your listeners, maybe a big
fraction, are like, "Yeah, like what are
the problems? That's a good question."
And then you're going to have the people
that actually deal with these things
like their heads already hit the desk
being like what are the problems? Like
what are the non problems? Like what
what works actually that's like a
shorter answer. I mean there are so many
problems and a lot of it is just like I
mean there are problems just
architecturally. These things are just
so I mean the problems spread to the
horizon so you can kind of start
wherever you want but I mean as like as
a really concrete example. Okay. Okay,
so the the BMC's, the computer within
the computer, that needs to be on its
own network. So you now have like not
one network, you got two networks. And
that network, by the way, that's the
network that you're going to log into to
like reset the machine when it's
otherwise unresponsive. So going into
the BMC, you can are you're able to
control the entire machine. Well, it's
like, all right, so now I've got a
second network that I need to manage.
What is running on the BMC? what's
running some ancient ancient version of
Linux that you got it's like well how do
I how do I patch that how do I like
manage the vulnerabilities with that
because if someone is able to root your
BMC they control the system so it's like
this is not and now you've got to go
deal with all of the operational hair
around that how do you upgrade that
system updating the BMC is I mean it's
like you've got this like second shadow
bad infrastructure that you have to go
manage generally not open source there's
something called open BMC
which people use to varying degrees, but
you're generally stuck with the
proprietary BMC. So, you're generally
stuck with ISO from HPE or IDRA from
Dell or the Super Micros BMC, the HP
BMC. And it is just excruciating pain.
This is assuming that by the way that
everything is behaving correctly. the
the problem is that these things often
don't behave correctly and then the
consequence of them not behaving
correctly is really dire because it's at
that lowest layer of the system. So I
mean I'll give you a concrete example a
customer of theirs reported to me. So I
won't disclose the vendor but let's just
say that a well-known vendor had an
issue with their temperature sensors
were broken and the thing would always
read basically the wrong value. So it
was the BMC that had to like invent its
own different kind of thermal control
loop and it would index on the actual
inrush current. They look at that at the
current that's going into the CPU to
adjust the fan speed. That's an
interesting idea. That doesn't work cuz
that's actually not the temperature. So
that software would crank the fans
whenever you had an inrush of current.
And this customer had a workload that
would spike the current. And when it
would spike the current, the fans would
kick up and then they would slowly
degrade over time. Well, this workload
was spiking the current faster than the
fans would degrade, but not fast enough
to actually heat up the part. And
ultimately, over a very long time, in a
very painful investigation, this
customer determined that like my fans
are cranked in my data center for no
reason. We're blowing cold air and it's
like this is on the order of like 100
watts a server of energy that you
shouldn't be spending and that comes
down to this kind of broken software
hardware interface at the lowest layer
that has real meaningful consequence in
terms of hundreds of kilowatts across a
data center. So this stuff has very very
very real consequence and it's such a
shadowy world. Part of the reason that
that your listeners that have dealt with
this, their heads will hit the desk is
because it is really aggravating to deal
with problems at this layer. You feel
powerless. You don't control or really
see the software that's on them. It's
generally proprietary. You're relying on
your vendor. Your vendor is telling you
that like, boy, I don't know. You're the
only customer seeing this. I mean, the
number of times I have heard that and I
I have pledged that we're we're not
going to say that at Oxide because it's
such an unactionable thing to say like
you're the only customer saying this.
It's like it feels like are you blaming
me for my problem? Feels like you're
blaming me for my problem. And what you
begin to realize is that to a degree
these folks are speaking their own truth
because the folks that are running at
real scale at hypers scale those folks
aren't Dell HP super micro customers.
They are actually they've done their own
thing. So it's like, yeah, the Dell's
not seeing that problem because they're
not running at the same scale. But when
you do run, you only have to run at
modest scale before these things just
become overwhelming in terms of the
headwind that they present to people
that want to deploy infrastructure.
Yeah. So maybe to help people get some
perspective, at what point do you think
that people start noticing or start
feeling these problems? Because I
imagine that if you just have a few
racks or
do you have a couple racks or the or you
wonder just wondering cuz no no no I
would think I think anyone who deploys
any number of servers especially now
especially if your experience is only in
the cloud you're going to be like what
the hell is this? I mean, just again,
just to get this thing working at all,
it's so hairy and so congealed, right?
It's not designed. I mean, nobody who is
setting up a rack of servers is going to
think to themselves like, "Yes, this is
the right way to go do it." This all
makes sense. I mean, it's a bag of
bolts. It's a bunch of parts that you're
putting together. And so, even at the
smallest scales, that stuff is painful.
Just architecturally, it's painful at
the small scale. But at least you can
get it working. I think the stuff that
then becomes debilitating at larger
scale are the things that are worse than
just like I can't like this thing is a
mess to get working. It's like the fan
issue where you are now seeing this over
you know hundreds of machines or
thousands of machines. So it is painful
at more or less all levels of scale.
There's there is no level at which the
PC which is really what this is this is
a the the personal computer architecture
from the 1980s and there is really no
level of scale where that's the right
thing to go deploy especially if what
you are trying to run is elastic
infrastructure a cloud because the other
thing is like we've kind of been talking
a lot about that hardware layer like
hardware is just the start like you
actually got to go put software on that
and actually run that as elastic
infrastructure So you need a hypervisor,
yes, but you need a lot more than that.
You need a distributed database. You
need web endpoints. You need a CLI. You
need all the stuff that you need to
actually go run an actual service of
compute or networking or storage. I
mean, and even for compute, there's a
ton of work to be done. And comput is by
far, I would say, the simplest of the
three. when you look at like network
services, storage services, there's a
whole bunch of stuff that you need to go
build in terms of distributed systems to
actually offer that as a cloud. So it I
mean it is painful at more or less every
level if you are trying to deploy cloud
computing on prem.
And for someone who doesn't have
experience building or working with this
type of infrastructure, when you talk
about a control plane, what does that do
in the context of the system? So control
plane is the thing that is everything
between your API request and that
infrastructure actually being acted
upon. So you go say, "Hey, I want to
provision a VM." Okay, great. We've got
a whole bunch of things we're going to
provision with that. We're going to
provision a VM. We're going to get some
storage that's going to go along with
that. That's got a network storage
service that's going to come out of. We
got a virtual network that we're going
to either create or attach to. We got a
a whole bunch of things we need to go do
for that. For all of these things, there
are metadata components that need we
need to keep track of this thing that
beyond the actual infrastructure that we
create. And then we need to go actually
like act on the actual compute elements,
the host OS, what have you, the
switches, what have you, and actually go
create these underlying things and then
connect them. And there's of course the
challenge of just getting that working
is a big challenge. But getting that
working robustly, getting that working
is, you know, when you go to provision a
VM, all the steps that need to happen
and what happens if one of those steps
fails along the way. What happens if,
you know, one thing we're very mindful
of is these kind of you get these long
tales of like generally our VM
provisioning happened within this time,
but we get these long tales where it
takes much longer. What's going on?
Where in this process are we actually
spending time? And there's a whole lot
of complexity that you need to go deal
with that that whole distributed system
that itself needs to be reliable and
available. So you need to be able to
what happens if you pull a sled or if a
sled fails? How does the system deal
with that? How does the system deal with
getting another sled added to the
system? Like how do you actually grow
this distributed system? And then how do
you update it? How do you actually go
from one version to the next? And all of
that has to happen across an air gap
where this is going to run as part of
the computer. So it is fractally
complicated. There is a lot of
complexity here in the software system
and all of that we call the control
plane and what exists at AWS at GCP at
Azure. you are hitting an endpoint
that's provisioning an EC2 instance for
you. There is an AWS control plane that
is doing all of this and has some of
these similar aspects and certainly some
of these similar challenges.
And for people who have run their own
servers with something like say VMware
or HyperV or Proxmox
are those in the same category?
Yeah, I mean a little bit. I mean it
kind of like vSphere yes VMware no. So
it's like VMware ESX is kind of a key
building block upon which you can build
something that is a more meaningful
distributed system. When it's just like
a machine that you're provisioning VMs
on, it's like okay well that's actually
you as the human might be the control
plane. Like that's a much easier
problem. But when you got tens hundreds
thousands of machines and you need to do
it robustly, you need something to
coordinate that activity and you know
you need to pick which sled you land on
and you need to be able to move these
things. You need to be able to update
that whole system. That's when you're
getting into a control plane. So, you
know, some of these things have kind of
edged into a control plane. Certainly
VMware now Broadcom has delivered
something that's kind of cloudish. I
think that for folks that are truly born
on the cloud, it still feels somewhat
like you're going backwards in time when
you look at these kind of on-rem
offerings. But it's got these aspects to
it for sure. and some of these other
things when you're just looking at KVM
or just looking looking at proxmox you
kind of need to connect it to other
broader things to turn it into something
that really looks like manageable
infrastructure and then many of those
projects are really they're either
proprietary products like vSphere or you
are really dealing with open source
projects that are not necessarily aimed
at the same level of scale you know you
look at a again a proxim or you look at
an open stack and you know open stack is
just a lot of things right I mean open
stack has got So many the OpenStack was
kind of a a free-for-all for every
infrastructure vendor. And I, you know,
there was a time people were like,
"Aren't you worried about all these
companies together that you know are
coming together for OpenStack?" I'm
like, "Haven't you ever worked for like
a company?" Like companies don't get
along, by the way. It's like having
multiple companies work together on a
thing. That's bad news, not good news.
And I think you know one of the things
that OpenStack has definitely struggled
with what actually there's so many
different kind of vendor elements in
there that it's very much not a product
it's a project that you're trying to run
but but that very much is in I mean
that's that's similar certainly in
spirit
and so I think this is kind of like you
were alluding to earlier the piece that
allows you to allocate compute storage
manage networking gives you that
experience of I can go to a web console
or I can use an API and I can spin up
machines, get them all connected. At the
end of the day, the control plane is
allowing you to do that in hopefully a
user-friendly way.
That's right. Yep. And and I mean in
order to do that in a modern way, it's
not just like a user friendly way. You
really need to have a CLI and a web UI
and an API. Those all need to be drawn
from the same kind of single ground
truth. like you don't want to have any
of those be an afterthought for the
other. You want to have the same way of
generating all of those different
endpoints entries into the system.
And if you take your time at joint as an
example, what kind of tools existed for
that versus how much did you have to
build inhouse as far as the hypervisor
and managing the compute and all that?
Yeah, so we built more or less
everything in house. I mean what you
have is and I think you know over time
we've gotten slightly better tools for
example at joint when we were building a
cloud at joint there wasn't really a
good distributed database so we were
using postgress as our database for
metadata and there were a lot of
challenges and postgress is not a
distributed database it's running with a
primary secondary architecture and
there's a bunch of issues there many of
which we discovered the hard way when we
were coming to oxide you much better
options to pick from. In terms of
distributed databases, there was a
period that now seems maybe potentially
brief in hindsight, but of a really
highquality open- source distributed
databases. So, there were really some
good ones to pick from. We've built on
cockroach DB on CRDB. So, that was a
really important component that we had
at Oxide that we didn't have at joint.
So, we were I wouldn't say we were
rolling our own distributed database. we
were just using Postgress and dealing
with an enormous amount of pain there in
terms of the surround on top of that.
You know, a control plane is much more
than a database obviously and you've got
to deal with there's a whole bunch of
software that you need to go write to be
able to transform these kind of API
requests into something that is reliable
infrastructure, right? And there's a lot
to that, especially when networking gets
in the mix, when storage gets in the
mix. There are a whole bunch of like
complicated steps that need to be done.
At Joiant, we in part because the
history of the company and like look,
this just is not going to sound good,
but it just is what it is and I'm just
going to own it. We did it all in Node
at Joiant, which I know sounds really
right now just sounds like you built it
with Tinker Toys. You okay? Did you
think it was you built the skyscraper
with Tinker Toys? It's like, well, okay,
we actually we had greater aspirations
for the Tinker Toys once upon a time.
But let's just say that that experiment
that experiment did ultimately end in a
predictable fashion and we decided that
maybe node was not going to be the best
decision long term. Joint was the
company behind Node.js back in the day.
Ryan doll worked for Joant and then we
landed that in a foundation in about
2015 something like that and began to
consider our world beyond node. A big
tool that we had in the arsenal when we
started Oxide is Rust. So indeed the
name of the company is a tip of the hat
to the language that we were pretty sure
we were going to be building a lot of
stuff in namely Rust. And Rust has been
huge for us a very important revolution
in programming languages. I think what
has been surprising is the sheer number
of layers at which we use Rust in terms
of we've done our own embedded firmware
in Rust. We've done in the host
operating system which is still largely
in C but very big components are in
Rust. The hypervisor provol is all in
rust and then of course the control
plane and distributed system on that is
all in rust. So that was a very
important thing that we very much did
not need to build ourselves. We were
able to really leverage a terrific
community. We were able to use and we've
done this at joint as well but at oxide
we've used umos as a host OS component
which our variant is called Helios.
We've used Beehive as that kind of in
kernel hypervisor component. We've made
use of a bunch of different open source
components to build this thing which has
been really really important for us and
open source components that didn't exist
even like five years prior as part of
why we felt that 2019 was the right time
to start the company when we started
Oxide
and you had mentioned that at joint you
had tried to build this in node what
were the what were the issues or the
challenges that you had doing that
oh boy yeah again we I kind of had
higher hopes Oops. In 2010, I would say
when we we sat on this, the problem that
we had just writ large, JavaScript is
really designed to allow as many people
on Earth to write a program as possible,
which is good. I mean, that's like
that's a lotable goal. The problem is
it's much more difficult to write really
rigorous software. We actually want to
be able to write rigorous software. And
it's actually okay if it's a little
harder to write rigorous software.
that's actually okay if it gets leads to
to more rigorous artifacts. But in
JavaScript, I mean a concrete example,
there's nothing to prevent you from
referencing a property that doesn't
actually exist in JavaScript. So if you
fatfinger a property name, you are
relying on something to tell you, by the
way, I think you've misspelled this
because there is no type definition for
this thing. And I don't know that you've
got one that's spelled correctly, one
that's spelled incorrectly that's often
undefined. And then when you actually go
so you've got this typo that is lurking
in what you want to be rigorous software
and if you don't execute that code like
you won't know it's there and then you
do execute that code and now you've got
an undefined object and now that's
either going to be an exception or it
can again depends on how that's handled.
It can be really difficult to determine
the origin of that error of that
programming. And that is a programmer
error. And one of the big challenges
that we had with node is that programmer
errors and operational errors like you
know I'm out of disk space is an
operational error. Those get conflated
and it becomes really hard and in fact I
think the language wanted to make it
easier to just kind of drive on in the
event of all errors and it's like
actually not what you want to do if
you're trying to build a reliable robust
system. So we had no end of issues.
We've got a lot of experience developing
rigorous systems again coming out of
operating systems development and so on
and we brought some of that rigor if
strangely to JavaScript. So one of the
things that we did is we brought a lot
of post-mortem diagnosibility and
observability to node. And so if one of
our node processes
died in production we would actually get
a core dump from that process. a core
dump that we could actually meaningfully
process. So we did a bunch of kind of
wild stuff. I mean actually wild stuff
where we could actually make sense of
the JavaScript objects in a binary core
dump and things that we thought were
really important and this is the the
rest of the world just looks at this
being like what the hell is this? I mean
it's so out of step with it. The problem
is that we were trying to bridge two
disconnected cultures of one developing
really rigorous software and really
designing it for production
diagnosibility and the other really
designing it to software to run in the
browser and for anyone to be able to
like you know kind of liven up a web
page right is kind of the origin of of
live script and then JavaScript and we
were kind of the only ones sitting at
the intersection of that and you begin
when you are the only ones sitting at
that kind of intersection and you just
are you're you're kind of fighting a
community all the time. And we just
realized that there were so many things
that the community wanted to do that we
felt are like no no this is going to
make software less diagnosible. It's
going to make it less robust. And then
you realize like I'm we're the only
voice in the room because we have got
desires for this language that it
doesn't have for itself. And this is
when you realize you're in a bad
relationship with software. It's time to
actually move on. And in fact actually
several years after we'd already kind of
broken up with Node and it was like it
was a bit of an acrimonious breakup
there was a famous slashinfamous fork of
Node called IOJS and this was viewed
because the community thought that joint
was being was not being an appropriate
steward of Node.js and was not allowing
more things to come into Node. And of
course, the reason that we of course
felt that we were being a careful
steward and we were actively resisting
those things that would cut against its
fitness for a production system. But the
way the community saw it and I think we
knew before the fork that's like this is
not working and we need to get this
thing out of our hands and we're the
wrong hands for this. This needs to be
in a foundation. So we kind of gone
through that breakup and maybe it was
two years after that that uh friend of
mine who was running the node summit
actually it's unfortunately now passed
away Charles Beer but Charles venture
capitalist great guy and Charles was
running node summit and came to me in
2017 he's like I really want you to
keynote node summit and I'm like Charles
I'm not going to do that I've got
nothing nice to say I'm the last person
you want to keynote he's like oh if you
have nothing nice to say you should
definitely keynote you're like oh god
okay Here we go. He's like, "No, I
really want you to talk about like you
should talk about the joint breakup with
no.js." I'm like, "Oh, man." And that
led to a talk that I'm really happy that
I gave because it was a very important
talk for me personally called platform
was a reflection of values and really
looking at the values that we had for
node and the values that node had for
itself and they didn't line up. Like
there's nobody in the node community
who's like, I don't want rigor. I hate
rigor. It's just that if they had to
choose between rigor and making the
language approachable, they would choose
approachability every single time. They
would never choose rigor. And that was a
big eye opener. I was if you watch this
talk because I knew that there's like
the audience was going to be filled with
people who had been a part of the fork
in 2014 I think was the fork the IOJS
fork I set a little bit of a trap for
the audience and the trap I said you
know I I kind of talked about the values
that we had and the aspirations we had
for node the aspirations that node had
for itself and how they were different
and I'm like look in hindsight like a
fracture was inevitable and in 2014 14
there was finally a fracture and do
people know what happened in 2014 and
you could listen to that talk everyone
almost says in unison like IoJS I'm like
oh right IOJS right that's actually not
what I was thinking of and I go to the
next slide and is a tweet from a guy
named TJ Holloway Chuckuk who was the
most prolific contributor to node and it
was his tweet also in 2014 before the
fork before the AOJS fork explaining
that he was leaving Node and that he was
going to go. And if you turn the volume
all the way up, you can hear the
audience gasp and it's just delicious
because the community had never really
confronted why TJ left. And I went
through a couple of folks, Felix, a
bunch of other folks, early node folks
that were there in 2010 were leaving in
2014. And they were going to go
primarily and they were going to go
because they were sick of the same
things that we were sick of. They had
hit the same things that we had hit and
they were frustrated. I really do
believe this that platforms do reflect
their own values and when you are making
a software decision, you should select
values that align with the values that
you have for that software. That's way
more important than other things that
people look at. I think people look at
for example quote unquote community size
way too frequently. Community size is
like eh maybe it can be fine. I've been
in very large communities node. I've
been in super small open source
communities like Alumos and Drace and a
bunch of others. There are strengths and
weaknesses to both approaches just as
like there's a strength to being in a
big city versus a small town. Me
personally, I'll take the small
community more or less every time
because the small community is almost
always self- selecting based on values.
And just for the same reason that I like
working at small companies or small
teams, there's a lot of value to be had
in a small community. It's not to say
that large communities value us, but
again, long answer to your question of
kind of where did things go south with
joint and node. They went south because
the values that we had and the values
the community had didn't line up. And
that was a very educational experience
as you might imagine.
Yeah. And given that you mentioned how
because of those values some people
moved from node to go and in the end for
much of what oxide is building you ended
up using rust. What would you say are
the values of go and and rust and how
did you end up choosing rust given that?
Yeah I mean well so the value for Yeah.
And so go I mean I understand why people
moved from node to go. Go to me was kind
of a lateral move. There were a bunch of
things that I go was still garbage
collected which I didn't like. Go also
is very strange in terms of there are
these kind of like these autocratic kind
of decisions that are very bizarre. I
mean generics is kind of a famous one
right where Go kind of as a point of
principle didn't have generics even
though Go itself actually the inards of
Go did have generics. It's just that you
a Go user weren't allowed to have them.
And I just think that the arguments
against generics were kind of
disingenuous and indeed like they ended
up adopting generics. And then there's
like some super weird stuff around like
they're very anti-assertion which is
like what how is someone against
assertions? It doesn't even make any
sense. But I was like, "Oh, nope. Okay,
there's a whole screed on it. Nope.
We're against assertions." And then, you
know, against versioning, there was
another thing like, you know, Rob Pike
has kind of famously been like, "You
should always just run on the latest
commit." And you're like, "Does that
make sense? I mean, we actually built
it." And so, there are a bunch of things
like that you're just like, "Okay, this
is just exhausting." And I mean, there's
some things about Go that are great and
plenty of other things that I just I'm
not a fan of. I think that the in and
like Go cares a lot about like compile
time. is super important for Go, right?
Is very quick compile time. I'm like,
okay, but that's like compile time is
not like it's not unimportant. It
doesn't have zero importance, but I've
got other things that are like lots more
important than that. What I really care
about is I want a high performing
artifact. And I wanted garbage
collection out of my life. I I got to
tell you, garbage collection to me is an
embodiment of this like larger problem
of where do you put cognitive load in
the software development process? And
what garbage collection is saying to me,
it is right for plenty of other people
and the software that they want to
develop. But for me and the software
that I want to develop, infrastructure
software, I don't want garbage
collection because I can solve the
memory allocation problem. I know when
I'm like done with something or not. I
mean it's like whether that's in C with
I mean it's actually like it's really
not that hard to not leak memory in a
Cbased system and you can give yourself
a lot of tooling that allows you to
diagnose where memory leaks are coming
from. So it's like that is a solvable
problem. There are other challenges with
that. But like when you are developing a
really sophisticated system that has
garbage collection, is using garbage
collection, you spend as much time
trying to dork with the garbage
collector to convince it to collect the
thing that you know is garbage. You're
like, I've got this thing. I know it's
garbage. Now I need to use these like
tips and tricks to get the garbage
collector. I mean, it's like it feels
like every Java performance issue goes
to like minus xxx use the other garbage
collector. Whatever one you're using,
use a different one. and using a
different approach. It's like you're in
the worst of all worlds where the reason
that garbage collection is helpful is
because the programmer doesn't have to
think at all about this problem, but now
you're actually dealing with these long
pauses in production. You're dealing
with all these other issues where
actually you need to think a lot about
it and it's kind of it's witchcraft.
It's this black box that you can't see
into. So it's like what problem have we
solved exactly? So the fact that go had
garbage collection it's like no I I do
not want like and then you get all the
other like weird fatwas and you know
everything else I'm like no thank you.
Go was a no thank you for me. I I get
why people like it or use it but that
was not going to be it. I'm like I want
C but I there are things I didn't like
about C too. I was looking for something
that was going to give me the
deterministic kind of artifact that I
got out of C. But I wanted library
support in C is tough because there's
it's all convention. You know, there's a
bunch of other things that are just
thorny. And I remember thinking vividly
in 2018. I'm like, well, it's rust or
bust. I'm going to go into Rust. And
when I did what a lot of people were
doing at that time and people have been
doing since of you know really getting
into Rust and really learning it
appreciating the difference in the the
model for sure the ownership model
people talk about is also obviously very
important. It was the error handling
that blew me away and the idea of like
algebraic types. I never really had
algebraic types and the ability to have
and for error handling is one of these
really you really appreciate these
things where it's like how do you deal
with a function that can either succeed
and return something or it can fail and
the way C deals with that is bad with
these kind of sentinels for errors and
you know does negative 1 mean failure
does zero mean failure some C functions
zero means failure traditionally in Unix
zero means success and like what if you
want to return a file descriptor you
know it's like oh and then it's like
okay then it'll be like zero through
positive n will be a valid result
negative numbers will be and like was it
negative one and I said air no or is it
a negative number that did I mean it's
like and that's all convention right
people do all those different things and
it's all convention and it's easy to get
wrong easy to have bugs can't be
statically checked and so on then what
go says is like well you're going to
have like two return values and then
you're going to have to like just like
constantly check all of these all the
time which is also kind of gross
JavaScript is like, hey, let's toss an
exception if if we don't like something.
If we see an error, we'll throw an
exception. There are a bunch of reasons
I don't like that. And you look at what
Rust does where it's like, no, no, no.
We're going to have these algebraic
types, which is to say, this thing can
be a this thing or a that thing, but it
has to be one of these. And by the way,
you don't get to process this thing
until you conditionally match on one of
these things. You're going to have to
have a pattern match on this thing to
determine if it's a this or a that. And
if it in the result type that you the
result is a generic where it's like it's
going to be either the thing that you
want to return, it's going to be an okay
that contains the thing you want to
return or it's going to be an error that
contains your error. And it forces your
code to deal with that. And what that
does is it shifts the cognitive load
from the person that is operating this
thing in production to the actual
developer that is in development. And
that to me is like I I love that shift
and that shift to me is really important
and that's what I was missing. That's
what Rust gives you. Rust forces you to
think about your code as you write it
but as a result you have an artifact
that is much more supportable, much more
sustainable and much faster. Yeah, it
sounds like you would rather take the
time during the development to think
about these issues because whether it's
garbage collection or it's air handling
at runtime when you're trying to solve a
problem then it's much more difficult
than having dealt with it to start with.
Yeah, absolutely. I and I just think
that like why also like if it's software
if it's again if it's infrastructure
software I mean the kind of the question
that you you should have when you're
writing software is how long is the
software going to live how many people
are going to use this software and if
you are writing an operating system the
answer for this thing that you're going
to write it's going to live for a long
time like if we just look at plenty of
aspects of the system that have been
around for decades it's going to live
for a long time and many many many
people are going to use it why would we
not expect people writing that software
to have more cognitive load when they're
writing it to give us something that's
going to be a better artifact? Now,
conversely, you're like, "Hey, I kind of
don't care about this and like I don't
know. I'm just like I want to see if
this whole thing works. I've got I like
I'm just stringing this together. I
don't like no software like we'll be
lucky if it survives until tonight." But
then like who cares? Yeah. Yeah. Garbage
collect, you know, if you're prototyping
something, whatever. And this is why you
really do get like different choices,
different technology choices depending
on the way that you want to solve the
problem at hand. And for the software
that I want to write, I do like that
cognitive load that is upfront. And
although I think I think the thing that
is really wild, that is the twist that I
don't think anyone really saw coming is
that in a in an LLM age, the cognitive
load up front almost needs an asterisk
on it because so much of that can be
assisted by an LLM. And now I mean I
would like to believe and maybe this is
me being optimistic that in the LLM age
we will see I mean Rust is a great fit
for the LLM age because the LLM itself
can get a lot of feedback about whether
the software that's written is correct
or not much more so than you can for
other environments. Yeah, that is a
interesting point in that I think when
people first started trying out the LLMs
to code, it was really good at these
maybe looser languages like Python or
JavaScript. and initially wasn't so good
at something like Rust, but it sounds
like as that improves, if it can write
it, then because of the rigor or the
memory management or the error handling
that the language is forcing you to do,
it might actually end up being a better
choice for people using LLMs. Yeah,
absolutely.
It gives you more certainty in the
artifact that you've delivered. I mean,
you know a lot about a Rust program that
compiles correctly. I mean, there are
certain classes of errors that you don't
have that you actually don't know on a C
program or a Go program or a JavaScript
program. I think that's going to be
really important. I think we are on the
cusp, maybe we've already seen it, this
kind of great bifurcation in the
software that we write where the
rigorous software becomes much more
important. we have this foundational
software that we're going to rely on as
much more bedrock and then we're going
to have much more software where that
rigor is not as much of a constraint
because the constraints are the ability
for it to be customized to my need and
done very quickly and it's going to feel
like I think two different worlds and I
think in an exciting way I think it's
going to be I think that the future is
definitely exciting for software
development
another interesting decision about the
oxide computer is you chose an operating
system that I think most people aren't
familiar with rather than rather than a
Linux or a free BSD. You chose I believe
it's Alumos. Is that how you pronounce
it?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, yes. So,
Alumos and Ulumos, which very much
inherits from open Solaris, which
inherits from the Solaris heritage,
which was Sunos 4.x X before that was
the Solaris itself is this unholy love
child of Sonos 4.X and the true kind of
BSD lineage and the AT&T lineage in Unix
and SVR4. In many ways I know that
people haven't necessarily heard of it
but it is true Unix in a real historical
sense in a way that Linux and even the
BSDs are not and there are aspects where
it shows it but in terms of it is an
idiosyncratic decision. It's not one
that we took lightly. People assume
like, oh, you know, it's a bunch of it's
a bunch of old Sun folks like of course
they're going to pick Lumos like this.
That's and we had a lot of operational
experience with with Smart OS at at
Joan. But that's a it's more nuance than
that. I would say it is true that a
bunch of the technologies that we have
developed over the years, we developed
them for good reasons and we don't want
to be without them. I mentioned the
postmortm diagnosibility of JavaScript.
Postm diagnosibility is really important
to us and to me. Debugability is really
important and debugability is not
something that other operating systems
have taken that seriously just to put it
bluntly. You can judge a lot about an
operating system by its built-in
debugger and there's not really a
built-in debugger present for Linux. But
it's more than just that. If you look at
Linux in particular, Linux is a kernel.
And you know this is something that
Torvald makes clear at you know in his
defense at more or less every juncture.
Linux is a kernel. And this is the kind
of the very famous you know the
stalmanism of like what you were calling
Linux I call canoe Linux and it's
obviously on the one hand a little bit
ridiculous on the other hand like not
wrong in that the software that you need
to actually have a functional system is
a lot more than just Linux you need a
lib right and there's actually more than
one lib is it going to be muscle is it
going to be gibbc there are some other
alternate lib's and part of the problem
is if you're going to use a Linux kernel
as the basis for a host operating
system. That's nowhere near enough
because you need to now build an entire
distro effectively of all these
different tools on top of that. And the
maintenance burden of that is off the
charts. And it's actually funny, one of
our colleagues, Laura Abbott, came from
Red Hat. And I'm like, well, this will
be interesting cuz I again my mind was
open, more open than it had been in, you
know, a long time about like maybe we
should use Linux. I don't know. And
Laura felt strongly that we shouldn't,
but for reasons that were different.
Laura was very concerned about what the
DRO management burden would be. And she
had really seen that upfront at Red Hat.
And she's like, "Do not make this
decision lightly that you've got to make
all these other decisions." And
something I really like I remember at
the time being like, "Okay, yeah, I
know. I get that." But then in the years
since I'm like, "Oh, wow. That's a
really big deal. That's a bigger deal
than I realized." So we don't have to do
that. we get an operating system that's
got a lot of stuff like built in. Now,
of course, it means that like we've also
it's a talk about small communities
definitely a small community and there
are challenges there too but it is one
that has allowed us to get the
technologies that we really need CFS
containers drace virtual networking a
bunch of things that we really needed we
had in place and then allowed us to also
move the system in a dimension that we
needed and wanted to move it. So for us
it's been the right decision. But I
think again the internet is kind of
disbelieving that we actually were at a
real juncture there. But we were we hand
actually at the moment where I was like
most potentially intrigued or at least
wanted to explore something like Linux
Torva was just on an absolute bender
against ZFS which he's done
occasionally. And I'm like this is dude
this is the wrong time to be on this
this ZFS tamper tantrum which he's again
done a couple of times but it was kind
of the and and a problem with Linux is
that ZFS is not a first class file
system. It's always been on the outside
because of this kind of these ridiculous
licensing concerns and it was a reminder
of like oh yeah write this. Yeah. Okay.
I think yeah we'll go our own way. Thank
you. And this choice of your operating
system as a user of an oxide computer
would they
you no you don't know I mean it's just
like you don't know if you're a user of
AWS you've got no idea what Nitro is or
Annaperna or these other things that are
like do you know whether they use KVM at
AWS? No, you've got no idea. I mean do
they use KVM or Zen? It's like the
answer is like well it depends on your
instance type and the age of the thing
and but like as a user that's opaque to
you. What you've got is like you want to
hit an API endpoint, you want to
provision an instance and you want to
run an operating system of your choice.
You want to run Windows or Linux or
FreeBSD or whatever as a in your cloud.
That's what you actually want to go do
and that's what we enable you to do.
And the oxide machine itself, I don't
think we've really explained physically
what it is. You know, what are people
going to be receiving?
What are the components? What is it? How
is it different? Yeah. What what would I
actually be buying and and getting into
my data center? So maybe you could talk
a little bit about what that actually
is.
Yeah. So you get a crate. You get a very
large crate and in that crate is a rack
and that rack is an oxides rack and that
rack has two switches and 32 compute
sleds that are in it. And that rack has
been designed holistically. So we have
designed all of these parts to work
together. We've got some very basic
things. We've got a DC bus bar in the
rack. So, we've got a power shelf that
rectifies from AC to DC. And then we run
DC up and down the back of the rack. And
our compute sleds blind mate into that
DC power. That is basic. And all of the
hyperscalers have a DC bus barbar based
system. You can't buy a DC bus barb
based system from Dell HP Super Micro
because in order to have a bus barbased
system, you really need to be designing
at at least the rack level because the
rack needs to be you can't just buy an
oxide sled. You need to buy the rack
that is going to contain it. And then we
very much designed the rack around the
switch. So the switch we actually have a
cabled back plane and in addition to
blind mating into power our compute
sleds blind made into networking. So the
networking is a passive cabled back
plane and it means there's no actual
cabling in the sled itself. So if you
want to take a sled out you just take
the sled out. There's no cables. One of
the challenges with the kind of
traditional server design and the
baseboard management controller has got
to be on two different networks. Well
ours is on two different networks too
but you don't see any of those because
it's all sitting on that cable back
plane. and our switch which has that
Intel Tofino at its core has a and
there's actually another switch that
serves as the switch for the service
processors on the system and then that's
all coherently interconnected. So what
you get is a real product and that thing
wheels into the data center. You get
power applied and you're on the tech
port doing the basic configuration we
need which basically like we need to
know who to talk to for time more or
less. We got to find you know there
there's some real basics that we need.
We need a BGP session and we need to be
able to actually like connect to a
network. But once we can do that we're
off and you're provisioning VMs, you're
provisioning storage, you're
provisioning networks, virtual networks
just like you're on the public cloud.
And one of the things that's been really
really fun because this is really
painful with traditional infrastructure.
It's this kind of bag of bolts approach.
It can take a comically long time. Well,
I'm talking like easily months to get
the gear has arrived. Get to the point
where devs are on there. You're like,
what takes months? It's like well glad
you asked. It's like we got the wrong
switch from this vendor. That server
came with the wrong rack rails. We're
missing the cabling over here. We got it
all together and the software vendor the
software didn't work and the software
vendor is pointing at the it's like
these things just like can take a long
time to get up and running with the
oxide rack that thing wheels in you
power it on you plug it in you get a BP
session and you're provisioning VMs and
one of the experiences that's been
really fun is to be with customers as
they are doing that for the first time
and be like oh my god I'm on the like
we're provisioning infrastructure like
can I can just like let my devs Is that
it? Like we just got this thing powered
on like 2 hours ago and that is really
really neat and very vindicating of the
approach that we've taken. It's really
exciting.
And for a listener who's never had to do
it the traditional way, what are all the
different things that they would need to
get into this rack to have the
equivalent?
You got to go buy switch from a switch
vendor. You got to go buy you're buying
your compute from someone else. Maybe
you're buying storage from someone else.
You're cabling it together. You got your
service, your BMC's got to be on a
network. So you got a separate switch
for that. You've got to have and then
you that's all just the hardware that
you gota get software on like what are
you doing for are you getting OpenStack?
Are you doing VMware? Are you doing
something else? And it's like then
that's all got to work. You've got to
get that imaged on there. You've got to
and it's like you're just kind of
building this thing as you go. I mean
there's just nothing that is you're the
one kind of literally cobbling this
thing together and it's just not a
product experience.
Yeah. Yeah. And I think the interesting
part was something you talked about
earlier too is that if something isn't
behaving the way you expect, for
example, the IO latency or maybe some
kind of compute issue. It seems like in
most of those cases, you really have no
one to turn to. You can go to Dell or HP
and they'll probably just shrug.
Well, yeah. There was kind of a tweet
when we were starting the company that
that we were all I think may have made
it into a slide deck or two where
someone said that they were dealing with
a a support issue with Dell and EMC and
they felt like they were talking to
their divorced parents. It's not
necessarily malicious because like a lot
of the problem is that like you have
these systems that are each
well-designed on their own or they're
welldesigned maybe that's putting that's
that is giving way too much credit.
They're designed on their own and then
they have an issue when you put them
together that each can plausibly blame
on the other. And this happens a lot
where you have it's like actually these
two things are kind of behaving somewhat
reasonably on their own but you put it
together and it it like the result is
terrible and the problem is it is the
end user that is left being like well
who helps me with my terrible. It's like
great. You each have made a convincing
case that it's not your problem. So I
guess it's who's I guess it's my problem
I guess. And that is what is really
really frustrating to people.
And I I'm curious back when you were at
Sun and and Sun was selling their own
servers, if somebody had a problem with
one of those servers, was that a case
where they could go to Sun and then Sun
would actually go and figure out, okay,
what's the problem here?
On its best days. Yeah, on its best
days. Its days were not always its best
days. Certainly the vision that I always
had for Sun Systems is that you'd be
able to do that. It was not always the
case. I started a storage group inside
of Sun called Fishworks in 2006 and we
partly wanted to really make good on
this idea of systems thinking. The fish
in Fishworks stands for fully integrated
software and hardware. And we learned a
whole set of painful lessons because we
were still relying on quote unquote
commodity hardware there and got bit by
a bunch of firmware we didn't control.
So throughout my career I have tried to
make good on this promise. But I really
feel it's only at oxide that we've been
able to control our fate sufficiently
from top to bottom to really make good
on it. And it shows in the experiences
that people are having which is really
great. And it sounds like maybe that's
primarily because the software running
on each of these components is in your
control so you're able to trace through
and see where the actual problem is
rather than having all these proprietary
vendors.
Yes, it is that for sure it is that we
just like have more of the components
under our own control. Don't want to
understate the importance of that. I
think it's also just the sense of
responsibility that we take that our
view is like we're going to own this
problem no matter what and we have now a
couple of concrete examples where we
have customer issues that like at the
end is like not a you know is it an
oxide problem it's like well no it fell
in a gap between oxide and a system we
were talking to and I think it's a point
of pride that we take responsibility for
taking that all the way to to root cause
sorry to be plugging our own podcast
here whenever the internet jokes that we
are actually a podcasting company that
is merely creating computers for content
creation and I'm not sure they're wrong
and so whenever we have any kind of like
crisis at oxad in terms of debugging a
problem or what have you were like this
is going to be great content and we had
one of these an episode that we called
other networks where we had a customer
where we took this particular switch and
talking to the oxide rack and the oxide
rack and the router were making like
reasonable decisions on their own, but
you added it up and it was a nightmare.
You know, we were able to get that debug
to root cause and even though you again
like our behavior was reasonable and it
behavior was reasonable, but we want to
be able to take responsibility for that.
So, I think it's a it is twofold. It's
the fact that we control these layers of
the stack, but then it's also very much
the sense that we have suffered at the
other end of this and what we want to be
able to do is really take on that
responsibility and get a customer
actually writed wherever the problem may
lie. I think that's a good spot to end
it on, but anything else you wanted to
mention?
No, it's great. I know we hit on a bunch
of things. Thanks for the wide-ranging
conversation. This was great.
So, if people want to check out what's
going on at Oxide, check out your
podcast.
Yeah, Oxide and Friends, you can join us
live in the Discord. We'd love to have
people join us live, but but check out
the podcast feed and check out the RFDs.
You can those are all out there as well.
Uh, and then check out the repos.
Everything we've talked about today is
open source. So people can dive in there
and see what we're actually doing. We
really pride ourselves on that
transparency. So we leave nothing to the
imagination. I think that sometimes
people are like, "Okay, maybe you guys
could share just a little bit less, you
know, so maybe transparency to a fault,
but there's a lot to go dive into if you
want to dive into oxide."
Yeah. I think for the people who are
actually managing these data centers and
working with traditional vendors,
transparency is exactly what they want
to hear. It is. It is. Yes. I think that
that transparency is We did have an
early customer that had an issue and we
wanted to get back to them, let them
know like, "Hey, we're working on your
issue." Customer's like, "No, no, I know
you're working on it. I'm watching the
GitHub issue." Actually, it's great. And
it's like, oh, okay. We love that. We
love the fact that people can see what
we're working on. We have always felt
there's much more to gain than there is
to lose.
Very cool. Well, Brian, thank you for
chatting with me today. This was fun.
Absolutely. Thanks for having me. This
was a lot of fun. and sorry to take you
into the filth that is the modern data
center.
All right. Well, this has been Jeremy
Jung for Software Engineering Radio.
Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by e
software magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
sea.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamse-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.